Guide to the Nikolai Nadezhin Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nikolai Nadezhin papers
1910-1957
GEN MSS 99
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.75
(6 boxes)
The papers contain letters to and from Nadezhin regarding social engagements, manuscript submissions, and requests for performances. The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters from Bryher discussing Nadezhin's work, literature in general, and personal matters. The collection also contains drafts of Nadezhin's articles, poetry, and autobiography, as well as biographical information, concert programs, and photographs.
Nadezhin, Nikolai Alexandrovich, 1885-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Papers were acquired by Yale University as a gift from Bryher in 1963.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in boxes 5-6 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files. Those in Box 6 are oversize newspaper or magazine clippings.
NIKOLAI ALEXANDROVICH NADEZHIN (1885-1959)
Nikolai Alexandrovich Nadezhin (also known as Nicholas Nadejine) was born on March 9, 1885 to a well-established family of the intelligentsia. His grandfather was Nikolai Petrovich Makarov, the lexicographer responsible for the first complete Russian/French dictionary. Nadezhin's early years were spent at the small ancestral manor called Funicovo near Tula where he was sent to be raised by his grandfather.
After matriculating from the "gymnasium" in 1905, Nadezhin began his first year at Moscow University, where he became a member of the Socialist Revolutionary Party and was soon involved in revolutionary activities. Early in 1906, Nadezhin was responsible for the armed hold-up of a local newspaper in order to produce a half million printed copies of the "Vyborg Manifesto." Later that year he was arrested and sentenced to life exile in Siberia, but managed to escape from captivity to Europe in 1908, never again to return to Russia. Eventually Nadezhin made his way to Italy and then to Capri.
In October 1918 Nadezhin met Compton Mackenzie, who owned a nearby villa on Capri. "Monty" Mackenzie invited Nadezhin, whom he nicknamed "Bim," to his villa as his guest. Nadezhin soon became the lover of Compton's wife, Faith Compton Mackenzie, and remained at the villa as her companion, with the complete knowledge of her husband, until 1922.
Between 1922 and 1938 Nadezhin lived in Australia, New Zealand, England and America, traveling with Russian emigrant theatrical groups as an opera singer. He wrote poetry in both Russian and English, and had three books published: Razuvieren'e (1925); Izbrannyia stikhotvoreniia (1954); and Knizhnaia Polka (1955). In 1927 he married a young Australian girl, Therese-Helen-Lydia Tritton, at the Russian Orthodox Church in London. Following Nadezhin's alleged affair with Mrs. Vera Oppenheimer, the couple were divorced in 1936. Two years later Lydia married the last Prime Minister of the Russian Provisory Government (1917), Alexandr Fyodorovich Kerensky, whom she had met through Nadezhin. That same year Nadezhin returned to Faith and helped her to move to Peace Close, a cottage in Somerset, after the sale of the villa in Capri. Nadezhin cared for Faith through her various illnesses and provided material for her writing for the rest of his life.
Sometime in the early 1940s Nadezhin met Bryher and soon began submitting his poems to her. Through their correspondence they developed a friendship that was to last until Nadezhin's death. During World War II Nadezhin served for a time as an interpreter for the British forces. Following the war, he joined the Russian Service of the British Broadcasting Corporation as a correspondent and worked in the War Office of the British government as well as other odd jobs. During the mid-1950s he assisted Compton Mackenzie with the publication of The Gramophone Monthly Review, contributing articles on Russian composers. Nadezhin died in the summer of 1959.
Scope and Contents
The Nikolai Nadezhin Papers consist primarily of manuscript writings and a small body of correspondence, spanning the years years 1910-1958. The Nadezhin Papers are divided into three series: Correspondence (Box 1), Writings (Boxes 2-3), and Personal Papers (Box 4).
Series I, Correspondence, includes letters to and from Nadezhin, dated between 1910 and 1958. This correspondence is arranged alphabetically within thirty-one incoming letter files, including one file of collective letters (postcards and holiday greetings signed by three or more people), one file of unidentified letters, and two files of third-party correspondence. The letters are written in Russian, Italian, and English and deal with manuscript submissions, requests for performances, and personal matters.
The bulk of the correspondence consists of the over 120 letters from Bryher, covering the period 1944-58. These letters discuss Nadezhin's poetry, Compton and Faith MacKenzie, Bryher's financial assistance to Nadezhin, personal matters, and the latest books they have read. Nadezhin's letters to Bryher are housed in the Bryher Papers. Other important correspondents are Gebby Katz, a woman with whom Nadezhin had an affair in 1914, and Faith Compton Mackenzie.
Series II, Writings, is divided into subseries of Prose Works, Poetry, Translations, and Writings of Others. Prose Works consists of fifteen folders of typescripts for his autobiography, entitled variously "Apology of an Iconoclast," "Apology of an Outsider," or "Lest I Forget," and eleven folders of short articles on Pushkin, Russian poetry, Nadezhin's travels, and printed reviews of Nadezhin's works. The autobiography covers the period 1889 through 1906 and describes Nadezhin's involvement with the Socialist Revolutionary Party in the Russian Revolution of 1905 and his subsequent exile to Siberia. Poetry consists of nine folders of Nadezhin's poems in Russian and English, one folder of unidentified poems, a published book of poetry, Izbrannia stikhotvoreniia, with a dedicatory poem to Bryher, and a review of his book of poems, Knizhnaia Polka. Translations contains one folder of poems by Rupert Brooke, Edmund Blunden, Walter De La Mare, Vita Sackville West, and Osbert Sitwell translated into Russian by Nadezhin. Works of Others is devoted to poems, translations, and articles by authors other than Nadezhin, including translations of poems by Pushkin, Lermontov, and Wolkonski, and a printed article by Sir Compton Mackenzie.
Series III, Personal Papers, consists of biographical material, photographs, concert programs from Nadezhin's performances, and miscellaneous material. The biographical material contains contracts, press releases, marriage and divorce certificates, and a photostat of a biographical note about Nadezhin written by Nina Berberova for Norman Holmes Pearson. The photographs are primarily of Nadezhin and members of his family between 1908 and 1928, with a few pictures of Sir Compton Mackenzie and Faith Compton Mackenzie. The concert programs date from 1913 to 1928. Box 4, folder 83 contains miscellaneous material, mostly undated, including a silhouette portrait of Bryher, magazine clippings, and a typescript copy of Peter the Great's will.
Authors, Exiled -- Great Britain; Poets, Russian -- 20th Century; Russians -- Great Britain; Amendola, Eva; Bryher, 1894-1983; Damanskai, A.; Katz, Gebby; Mackenzie, Compton, 1883-1972; Mackenzie, Faith Compton, 1878-1960; Nadezhin, Nikolai Alexandrovich, 1885-1959
- Correspondence, 1910-58; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence is divided into two subseries: Nadezhin Correspondence and Third-Party Correspondence. All letters in Nadezhin Correspondence are incoming except for one letter to Faith Compton Mackenzie, February 16, 1941. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by surname. Collective letters and unidentified correspondence are placed at the end of the subseries. Third-Party Correspondence consists of third party letters to Faith Compton MacKenzie, Lydia (Tritton) Nadezhin, and others.
  - NADEZHIN CORRESPONDENCE
    - Amendola, Eva, 1915-16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Asquith, Anthony, 1936 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Batchinsky, Mme. A., 1938 Feb 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Belloc, Elizabeth, n.d
    - Bikerman, L., 1944-54 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Borghese, Genoveffa, 1915 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1947
    - Bryher, 1944-58 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
    - Cerio, Edwin, 1958 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chelishchev [?], Olga, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chernova, Olga, 1910 Jul 3
    - Chernoyarov, Georgii, n.y. Jan 27
    - Connell, John, 1929
    - Damanskai, A., 1956-58 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Douglas, Norman, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Evreinov, A., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Feature Productions, 1930 Aug 28
    - Filipov, Nikolai, 1909 Apr 10
    - Guizs, Maria, n.d.
    - Imperial Russian Consulate, Rome, 1914 Dec [?]
    - Katz, Gebby, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Betty Sandburg, Box 1, folder 22
    - Katz, Mikael, 1936 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - London Film Productions, 1936 Jun 24
    - Mackenzie, Compton, Sir, 1941-52 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Mackenzie, Faith Compton, 1941-58 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Mendl, Charles, 1928 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Morison, W. A., 1946 Dec 23
    - Miasoedov, Aleksandr, 1949-55 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Nabokov, Vladimir Dmitrievich, 1921 Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Ospedale Militare di Riserva, 1916 Jan 3
    - Petrovich, T., 1917 Apr 4
    - Philharmonic Society of Guitarists, 1948-54
    - Russian Club of Australia, 1930 Jun 14
    - Russian Embassy, Rome: certificate of Nadezhin's government service from February 16-March 1, 1917, n.d.
    - Sabline, E., 1936-39
    - Sandburg, Betty, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Sanin, Alexander Akimovich, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Savelli, E.[?], n.d.
    - Schaefer, Herman Schaefer, Johanna, 1950-57 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Sergei, Archimandrite (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Shcheglov, Sasha (sister), 1916-33 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Stone, Christopher, 1921 Jan 14, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Stuart, Mary, 1956 Oct 15
    - Vinogradov, Igor, 1953 Dec 31
    - Vitoshinsky, V., 1931 Aug 3
    - Wrenn, C. L., 1955 Jan 19
    - Collective letters, 1910-16 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified correspondence, 1908-58 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - THIRD-PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bryher and H.D.: (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - to Faith Compton Mackenzie, 1957 Nov 9
    - Cunard, Nancy:
      - to Faith Compton Mackenzie, 1954 Oct 19
    - Eglise Russe, Paris: (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - to Jacob Smirnoff, 1910 May 26
    - Seraphim, Archbishop:
      - to Lydia Nadezhina (Tritton), n.d.
- Writings, 1917-56; Series II; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is divided into the alpha- betically arranged subseries Prose Works, Poetry, Translations, and Works of Others. Within the subseries Poetry the poems are arranged by title or first line.
  - PROSE WORKS
    - "A. Grechaninov": printed article from The Gramophone, 1938 Mar (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "Apology of an Iconoclast": typescript draft, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
    - "Apology of an Outsider": typescript draft, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36-41)
    - Miscellaneous pages from "Apology of an Iconoclast," "Apology of an Outsider," and "Lest I Forget": typescript drafts with holograph corrections by Nadezhin and Bryher (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Apology of an Outsider": final typescript draft, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43-47)
    - Autobiographical comments on émigré life: holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Broadcast on Pushkin: typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - "Chaliapin (In memoriam, 1873-1938)": printed article from The Gramophone, 1938 May (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "A Journey to South Africa": two typescript drafts, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Notes, biographical and historical: holograph manuscript (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "Pushkin Commemoration Evening in Chelsea!": typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Slovo o Russkoi Poezii": holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - "Strany i goroda. Otplytie v' Yuzhnuyu Afriku": printed article, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "Twenty-five Centuries of Russian Music": typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "Ubiitsa": typescript fragment of a play, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Untitled Essay on Poetry: holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "Zapiski puteshestvennika [Notes of a traveler]": holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - "Zapiski puteshestvennika": printed article from Novayazarya, two copies, 1930 Jul 17 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - POETRY
    - "Arbiter Grammaticorum": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - "Atomic Boomerang": typescript, n.d.
    - "Az" pravoslaviia bliustitel'...": typescript, carbon, 1951 Nov 1
    - "Balada o Varilo": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Beyond the Curtain": typescript
    - "Byla izmenoi i kovarstvom...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Cherez polia, lesa i vesi...": holograph manuscript, signed, n.d.
    - "Chto by schastlivym" byt', poetu...": mimeograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "Le dernier chapitre": typescript, corrected, n.d.
    - "Disregarding your own and your country's welfare...": three typescript drafts, carbon
    - "Esli by Tsaria Goroxa...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Festival of Britain": typescript, 1951 Mar 24
    - "Graf Bobrinskii iia na sluzhbe...": typescript, corrected, 1947 May 11
    - "Grokhot rushashchikhsia zdanii..." and "Mechtatelem ya i poetom...": typescript fragments, corrected (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "The half-forgotten memories...": proof page from Izbrannyia stikhotvoreniia, corrected, [1954]
    - "I ia pytalsia, stav poetom...": holograph manuscript, holograph note on reverse, n.d.
    - "In memoriam": typescript, corrected, and carbon
    - "Istoriia rusi": printed version from Russkoye Voskresenie, 4 copies, 1955 Aug 11 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "Kak zhe vremia vy provodite...": typescript, carbon, corrected, 1946 Feb 3 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - "Kak mysh' biegushchaia k" podpol'iu...": typescript, carbon, corrected, 1917 Apr
    - "Khotia vy...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Kogda avora sumrak[?]...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Kogda svershilis' sroki...": typescript, and carbon, corrected
    - "Kogda usnu ia...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Kolybel'naia": typescript, n.d.
    - "Korpet' nad rifmoi vsiakii vprave...": typescript, and carbon
    - "Lili Bulianzhe" and two unidentified poems: holograph manuscript, 1916-30 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - "London 1940-1941" and one unidentified poem: holograph manuscript
    - "Malbrough s'en va-t-en guerre": typescript, corrected, n.d.
    - "My zhalvemsia na sud'bu...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Na more": typescript, n.d.
    - "Na polovine dlinnoï zhiznennoï dorogi...": two typescript copies, corrected, n.d.
    - "Na voennom polozhenii": typescript, signed, 1939 Fall
    - "Ne budorlzhit' zdes' sharmanka..." and fragments: holograph manuscript, signed, 1952
    - "Neapol'": typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - "Ni klochka ne vidno neba...": typescript, n.d.
    - "Ochen'mne prishlas', Natasha...": holograph manuscript, signed, n.d.
    - "Otvet na pis'mo starogo druga": typescript, and carbon
    - "Po k nam doshedshim slukham...": typescript, corrected, n.d.
    - "Po pokhodnomu odetymi...": typescript fragment, carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - "Podchiniv sebia zheleznym...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Potomstvo proklyanet" i zakleimit" prezren'em"...": typescript, corrected, 1917 Sep 4-17
    - "Priznan'ia talantam svoim ne nashel...": typescript, corrected, signed, and carbon
    - "Road to Rome": typescript, corrected, 1944 Feb
    - "Rodina": typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - "Rossii": two typescript drafts, corrected, n.d.
    - "Rule Britannia": typescript, corrected, n.d.
    - "Skroz' trevolnen'ia zhnznn buron...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Stol' rezkoe mnen'e pozhalui, neskromno...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Strakhi smertnye mn" ne v" novinku..." and two unidentified poems: holograph manuscript, 1930-31
    - "Teloslozhene tsiklopa...": typescript, with holograph note, n.d.
    - "Tempus fugit: pray to heaven...": typescript, carbon, [1952] (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - "Ternistyi put'": holograph manuscript, signed, n.d.
    - "There was some jolly singing...": holograph manuscript, n.d.
    - "Those frosty nights and misty mornings...": typescript, translation of two stanzas from Razuvieren'e, removed from a copy inscribed "for Bryher, 16 Sep 1953"
    - "Unynie" and one unidentified poem: holograph manuscript, 1936
    - "Vot golova-uma palata...": typescript, 1947 Jul 26
    - "When at long last I am quite dead...": miscellaneous stanzas, typescript, corrected, with fragment copy, [1952]
    - "Za Kchlisami mikrofona": typescript verse play, n.d.
    - Izbrannyia stikhotvoreniia, (London, 1954): printed version, with dedicatory poem "To Bryher" (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Knizhnaia Polka: review by Inc.[?], clipped from newspaper, 2 copies, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Unidentified poems, 1934-42, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - TRANSLATIONS
    - "Kogda umru i ia..." and "Po snezhroi tropinke iz chashchi...": typescript, translations of poems by Rupert Brooke and Osbert Sitwell (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - "Saksonskaia pesn'" and "Po snezhnoi tropinke...": typescript, translations, and carbon, of poems by Vita Sackville West and Osbert Sitwell
    - "Kogda ia vnemliu muzyke..." and "Kogda umru i ia, vy,..." and "Kakaia krasota v polete...": typescript translations, with corrections, of poems by Walter De La Mare, Rupert Brooke, and Edmund Blunden
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Blunden, Edmund, and Roy Campbell, typescript copies of poems (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Damanskai, A., "Nieistoshchimaia tema": printed article, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Kamenetsky, B., "Literaturnyia zametski," printed review article in Rul, 1925 Feb 25 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Kotënok, "To a Russian Gentleman Who Sang at a Party", 1957 Nov 13 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Mackenzie, Compton, Sir, "Youth Has Never Had It So Good article, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Miasoedov, Aleksandr, miscellaneous fragments of Russian poems translated into French; all on same page (Box 3, Folder 80)
      - "Poltava" - Aleksandr Pushkin "A la Princesse" - Z. Wolkonski "Mtsyri" - Mikhail I. Lermontov "Eugene Onegin" - Aleksandr Pushkin "Souvenir" - Aleksandr Pushkin, 1937 Jul
    - Poem and note
    - Slovtsov, P., "Gitara i slovar'": printed article about Makarov, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 81)
- Personal Papers, 1908-57; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series III, Personal Papers, consists of chronologically arranged biographical information on Nadezhin, concert programs, photographs, and miscellaneous papers.
  - Biographical
    - Contract with Madame Lydia Kyasht's Russian School of Dancing, 1924 Dec 1 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Marriage certificate to Lydia Ellen Tritton, 1927
    - Press release on "Nicolai Nadejine, The Well Known Baritone", [c.1928?]
    - Passenger List R.M.S. "Samaria", 1930 Dec 12
    - Naturalization certificate, 1934 Apr 20
    - Divorce petition, 1936 Feb 24
    - Berberova, Nina: biographical sketch of Nadezhin, signed "N.B.", with a letter to Norman Holmes Pearson, photostat, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Concert Programs (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Nadezhin, Nikolai, 1908
    - Shcheglov, Vladimir Nikolaevich, half-brother of Nikolai Nadezhine, 1910 Feb
    - Nadezhinek, Vikto (postcard), half-brother of Nikolai Nadezhine, 1910 Mar 12
    - MacKenzie, Compton, Group photo of marchers inscribed "Monty at back, prob 1914"
    - Group photo, Capri, 1920
    - Photograph of wedding to Lydia Tritton, [1927]
    - Magazine clipping of wedding photo to E.T.N. [Lydia] Tritton, [1927]
    - "Nicolai Nadejine, The well-known baritone", [c.1928]
    - Nadezhin, 1930[?] May
    - "Nora", 1949
    - House (Lerchenhof), 1957
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Lamb, Martha J., obituary clipped from magazine, [c.1893]
    - Bryher, silhouette, n.d.
    - Recipe, n.d.
    - Sex and Sex Worship: review by O. A. Wall, St. Louis, 1919
    - Silhouette [subject unknown], n.d.
    - "Will of Peter I of Russia": typescript, taken from The History of Russia, Walter K. Kelly, (London, 1854)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Boxes 5 and 6, Restricted Fragile Papers, contain fragile originals. Box 6 houses oversize papers. The material is arranged in folder order separately in both Box 5 and Box 6. It may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 3, folder 60 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Box 3, folder 61 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Box 3, folder 65 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Box 3, folder 66 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Box 3, folder 68 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Box 3, folder 70 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Box 3, folder 74 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Box 3, folder 55 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Box 3, folder 64 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Box 3, folder 77 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Box 3, folder 79 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Box 3, folder 81 (Box 6, Folder 98)